Finding Aid for University of Michigan. Faculty Women’s Club records, 1921-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University of Michigan. Faculty Women’s Club records 1921-2004
University of Michigan. Faculty Women’s Club.
1 oversize volumes
14.5 linear feet (in 15 boxes)
87165 Bimu;M3;2
Proceedings, treasurer's reports, committee reports, scrapbooks, and various administrative records.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were first deposited with the MHC in 1941; periodic accessions have been received since then. Donor no. 1428.
Further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
On October 26, 1921, Nina Burton, wife of U-M President Marion Leroy Burton, gathered together at the President's House fifty women - wives of professors, department heads, deans, and administrative officers - to form a faculty women's club. Then, as now, the purpose of the club was to promote acquaintance, friendship, and collegiality among its members.
The Faculty Women's Club (FWC) was designed so that women faculty and wives of faculty members who shared similar interests would be able to form close friendships in small interest groups. In 1922, the FWC had three interest sections: Drama, Day Nursery and Athletics. Today, there are 39 active sections reflecting the diverse interests, activities and enthusiasms of the members.
Special care has always been taken to welcome newcomers and visiting faculty to the university family. Each interest group has always permitted a limited number of guests from the community, creating a "Town and Gown" atmosphere. The original group of 50 ladies has grown to over 600.
In its early years, the University provided a red brick house on South Ingalls. When the Michigan League was completed in the Spring of 1929, the FWC moved its activities to the League rooms, where many of the major events are still held. The FWC sponsors three major gatherings a year; the Fall Reception, a Mid-Winter Party, and the Spring Luncheon and Annual Membership and Business Meeting.
The University of Michigan Faculty Women's Club record group contains materials from 1921-2003, which document the work of this organization to promote friendship and collegiality among women faculty and wives of faculty members. The record group contains information about the activities and administrative procedures of the club. The record group is arranged in five series: Administration, Newcomers, Interest Groups, Events and History.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Faculty.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ackley, Gardner.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Women--Organizations.; Woodcock, Leonard.; University of Michigan. Faculty Women's Club.; University of Michigan--Presidents.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Videotapes.
- Administration 1921-2000
  The Administration series is arranged alphabetically by topic. It includes the club's by-laws, records of committees and club officers, and minutes and reports. In addition, the series contains newsletters sent to the members and club yearbooks with information regarding the history of the club and the interest groups. Membership lists dating from 1921-1999 are also included in this series.
  - By-laws 1967-1993, undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Club Yearbooks
    - 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - 1986-2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - By-Laws Committee 1966-1967, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Budget Committee Minutes 1980-1985, 1990 (except 1982) (Box 1)
    - Constitution Study Committee 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Dance Committee
      - Records 1931-1933, 1949-1971, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Dance Planning 1967-1971 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
    - Liaison committee regarding Dearborn and Flint relations 1966-1970 (Box 1)
    - Membership Committee
      - General Information 1975, 1979, 1982-1984 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence 1960-1968 (Box 1)
      - Reports 1961-1985 (Box 1)
    - Millennium Committee
      - Endowment 1998-2000 (Box 1)
      - Minutes 1998-2000 (Box 1)
      - Reports 1998-2000 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Newcomers Committee
      - Annual Reports 1989-1993 (Box 1)
      - Rules of Procedure 1975, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Nominating Committee
      - General Information 1949-1968 (Box 1)
      - Reports 1950-1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Refreshments Committee 1933-1938 (Box 1)
    - Social Committee
      - Events 1967, 1972, 1978, 1979-1980, 1983-1985, 1991-1993, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Reports 1970-1982, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1926-1949 (Box 14)
    - 1951-1958 (Box 14)
    - 1963-1968 (Box 14)
    - 1970-1973 (Box 14)
    - 1990 2001 (Box 14)
  - Description of Duties for Officers and Committee Chairmen 1961-1980, 1983-1984, 1991 (Box 14)
  - Financial Records
    - 1976-1998 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Membership Lists
    - 1957-1999 undated, 12 folders (Box 14)
    - Early Membership Cards 1921-1944 (in boxes) (Box 2)
    - Membership Qualifications 1984-1986, undated (Box 2)
  - Minutes
    - Annual Meetings
      - 1949-1954 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1964 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1994 1999, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Board of Directors Meetings 1966-2000, 2003-2004, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Executive Committee Meetings 1954-1972, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Newsletters 1949-2003 (with some exceptions), 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Officers
    - Officers Lists 1967-1968, 1974-1999 (Box 3)
    - President
      - Correspondence 1978-1993, 1996-2001, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Duties 1983-1994 (Box 3)
      - President's Notebook
        - 1966-1967 (Box 3)
        - 1971-1973, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - 1975-1978, 3 folders (Box 3)
        - 1978-1991 (except 1980, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Program Chairman's Notebooks 1947, 1957-1962, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Secretary's Notes 1994-1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Treasurer's Notebook 1965-1971, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Proceedings of the Faculty Women's Club
    - 1921-1941, 2 volumes (Box 4)
      (original and copy)
    - 1941-1951, 3 volumes (Box 4)
      (original, fragmentary and copy)
    - 1951-1961 (Box 5)
    - 1961-1971, 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Reports from Board Members
    - 1921-1987 (except 1962-1963), 21 folders (Box 5)
    - 1987-1994 1998-1999, 4 folders (Box 6)
- Newcomers 1921-1986
  The Newcomers series documents the work of the club with new members. Minutes, reports and directories of the Newcomers Board is included in this series. There are also reports and information from the Newcomers' interest groups. Activities like the Welcoming Party and Fashion Show are also included in this series.
  - Information Guide 1979-1985, 1992 (Box 6)
  - Activities
    - Deck the Halls Party 1970 (Box 6)
    - Fashion Show 1966-1971 (Box 6)
    - Holiday Creations undated (Box 6)
    - Welcoming Parties 1965-1982, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
    - Wine-Tasting Party and Welcoming Coffees 1970-1971 (Box 6)
    - Other Activities 1966, 1971, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
  - Board Directories 1973-1986 (except 1975 and 1984) (Box 6)
  - Board Meetings 1970-1986, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Board Reports 1962-1986, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Newcomers Sections
    - Sections Descriptions undated (Box 6)
    - Membership Lists 1980-1985 (Box 6)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1928, 1930, 1937-1938, 1948 (Box 6)
      - 1962-1988, 3 folders (Box 6)
- Interest Sections 1923-2000
  The Interest Groups series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the group. The sections are organized by the following interest groups: Art, Books, Bridge, Garden, Home, Language and Drama, Special Interests, and Sports. Each interest group has its own sections. This series consists mainly of the annual sections reports, but it also includes historical information, minutes and notebooks from some of the sections.
  - Membership and Annual Reports 1976-1998/1999, 9 folders (Box 6)
  - Membership and Annual Reports 1999/2000-2001/2002, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous 1973-1995 (Box 7)
  - Procedures for Section Administration 1970-1985 (Box 7)
  - Art Groups
    - Art History Section
      - History and General Information 1966-1968, 1970-1971, 1990-1991, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
      - Membership Lists 1954-1969 (Box 7)
      - Minutes 1956-1967, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Programs 1956-1969, 1990-2000 (Box 7)
      - Resource Information 1989-1996 (Box 7)
      - Section Notebook 1941-1953 (Box 7)
    - Art Study Section
      - Photographs Album, 1984-1993 (Box 7)
      - Photographs and Miscellaneous, 1998-2000 (Box 7)
      - Annual Reports and Membership 1976-1990 (Box 7)
    - Art Tours Section
      - Membership Lists 1968-1970, 1974-1987 (Box 7)
      - Tours 1969-1988, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Groups Annual Section Reports 1923-1924, 1954-1985, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Books Groups
    - Bookshelf and Stage Section
      - General Information 1964-1987 (Box 7)
      - Membership Lists 1964-1987 (Box 7)
      - Meetings Notebook 1933-1941 (Box 7)
      - Records Notebook 1927-1960, 2 volumes (Box 8)
    - Evening Book Review Section
      - General Information undated (Box 8)
      - Membership Lists 1948-1997, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Minutes 1927-1933, 1986-1993, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Activities and Programs 1954-1977, 1984-1997 (Box 8)
      - Newspaper Clippings 1949-1958, 1974, 1975, 1980 (Box 8)
      - Secretary's Records 1951-1997, 9 folders (Box 8)
    - Groups Annual Section Reports 1948-1997, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Bridge Groups
    - Duplicate Bridge Section 1977-1988 (Box 8)
    - Groups Annual Reports 1962-1978, 1983-1984 (Box 8)
  - Food Groups
    - Tuesday Night Kitchen Scholars
      - Administrative Records 1976-1991 (Box 8)
      - Recipes and Programs 1966-2002, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Garden Groups
    - Garden Section (Box 9)
      - Ann Arbor Garden Club Handbook 1949 (Box 9)
      - History and General Information 1923, 1975-1991 (Box 9)
      - Membership Lists 1929-1949, 1976-1984 (except 1979-1980) (Box 9)
      - Minutes
        - 1927-1949, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - 1965-1984, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Correspondence 1962, 1974-1975, 1980-1982 (Box 9)
      - Program booklets (Box 9)
      - Programs, reports, membership lists 1960-1979 (Box 9)
      - Programs, minutes, reports 1980-1998 (Box 9)
    - Groups Annual Section Reports 1962-1976, 1983-1984 (Box 9)
  - Home Groups
    - Groups Annual Reports 1962-1976, 1988 (Box 9)
  - Language and Drama Groups
    - Tuesday Play Reading Section
      - Membership Lists 1962-1991 (Box 9)
      - Notebook of Activities
        - 1956-1971 (Box 9)
        - 1979-1993 (Box 9)
      - Secretary's Notebook 1946-1956 (Box 9)
      - Treasurer's Notebook 1946-1972 (Box 9)
    - Groups Annual Reports 1963-1978, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Special Interests Groups
    - Groups Annual Reports 1923, 1962-1976 (Box 9)
  - Sports Groups
    - Hiking/Cross Country Skiing Section
      - General Information 1983-1988 (except 1984, 1986) (Box 9)
      - Membership Lists 1973-1974 (Box 9)
      - Annual Schedules 1974-1975 (Box 9)
    - Ice Skating Section
      - General Information 1959-1968 (Box 9)
      - Membership Lists 1957-1959, 1974-1977 (Box 9)
      - Treasurer's Book 1965-1977 (Box 9)
    - Square Dance Section
      - History 1988-1992 (Box 10)
      - Membership Lists 1953-1994, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Callers 1958, 1978-1994 (Box 10)
      - Committees 1951, 1979-1994 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence 1955-1958, 1981-1991 (Box 10)
      - Dance Reports 1976-1994 (except 1977), 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Duties 1956, 1985-1994 (Box 10)
      - Flyers/Member Letters 1954-1994, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Minutes 1950-1994, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - News Clippings 1954-1976 (Box 10)
      - Press Notices 1984, 1989-1994 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous 1950, 1954, 1990, 1993 (Box 10)
    - Swim Club membership cards (Box 10)
    - Groups Annual Reports 1952-1988, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Other Sections
    - Nursery Section
      - Minutes 1923-1926 (Box 10)
      - Reports 1925-1931 (Box 10)
    - Red Carpet Section
      - Annual Reports 1962-1971 (Box 10)
    - University Affairs Section
      - Annual Reports 1962-1971 (except 1969) (Box 10)
- Events 1925-1998
  The Events series is arranged alphabetically by event name. This series documents not only the activities that the club does for the members, but also other events and projects in which the club had participated. The series contains the records of the participation of the club in the Big Ten Conference, in which they share experiences with other university women clubs from the Big Ten Conference. It also includes correspondence, photos and newspaper clippings regarding a FWC project to send windbreakers to servicemen of the United Nations.
  - 40 Years in Song in Rhyme 1962 (Box 10)
  - 60th Anniversary 1981 (Box 10)
  - 70th Anniversary (Box 10)
  - 75th Anniversary
    - Art History Section 1997 (Box 10)
    - Commemorative Quilt 1996 (Box 10)
    - Cookbook 1995-1997 (Box 10)
    - General Information and Meeting Minutes 1994-1996 (Box 10)
    - Spring Luncheon 1997 (Box 10)
    - Videotape (including Quilt Presentation and Spring Luncheon), 1996-1997, VHS format (Box 10)
  - Annual Programs 1925-1948 (Box 10)
  - Big Ten Conference
    - Conference Information 1984-1985 (Box 11)
    - Conference Host Committee Papers 1984-1986 (Box 11)
    - Conference Report July 1985 (Box 11)
    - Files of Attendance 1984-1985 (Box 11)
    - Meeting at UW-Madison June 19-21, 1987 (Box 11)
    - Photographs 1987 (Box 11)
    - Sally Fleming Notebook 1984-1986 (Box 11)
  - Christmas Coffee 1963-1969 (Box 11)
  - Dinner Dance 1980-1991, 1995, 1998 (Box 11)
  - Faculty Fun Night 1963-1967, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Fall Reception 1966, 1969, 1980-1990, 1995, 1998 (Box 11)
  - Historical Pageant 1932 (Box 11)
  - Holiday Reception 1981-1996 (Box 11)
  - Hospitality for World Visitors 1991-1992 (Box 11)
  - Lectures and Libations 1985-1990 (Box 11)
  - Norwegian Relief
    - Correspondence 1945 (Box 11)
  - Open Houses 1979-1981 (Box 11)
  - President's Tea 1960 (Box 11)
  - Project of Sending Windbreakers to Servicemen
    - Correspondence 1941-1943, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Newspaper Clippings and Photographs, 1941-1944 (Box 11)
  - Spring Luncheon 1966-1999, 3 folders (Box 11)
  - A Tribute to President and Mrs. Fleming January 24, 1979 (Box 11)
  - University Wives 1965-1973 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Events 1932, 1945-1947, 1955, 1987 (Box 11)
  - Videotape, Ackley and Woodcock FWC Presentation, October 18, 1988, VHS format (Box 12)
  - Photo Album undated (Box 12)
- History 1921-1994
  The History series contains various types of materials. In the 1990s, a series of oral history interviews were conducted with prominent members of the FWC. The audiotapes and transcripts of some of these interviews are included here. This series also includes three scrapbooks of photographs and newspaper clippings. The scrapbooks were compiled by the club's history committee. It includes photographs of many club presidents and other officers and of club events and guest speakers as well as newspaper clippings and a few historical documents.
  - Clippings 1942-1994 (Box 12)
  - Historical Research 1921-1996, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - History files (Box 15)
  - Obituaries undated (Box 12)
  - Oral History
    - Audiotapes 1994, 6 audiocassettes (Box 12)
    - Quotes 1921-1994 (Box 12)
    - Transcripts 1992-1994, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Sections undated (Box 12)
  - Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings
    - 1922-1970, 2 volumes (Box 13)
    - 1971-1985 (Volume 1)
      (includes photographs)